<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <channel>
        <title>Latest News from Science Magazine</title>
        <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/rss/news_current.xml</link>
        <description>Editable in modal at Format : RSS Feed | Settings : RSS Description</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 01:43:45 -0500</pubDate>
        
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Drug, HIV crises hit HHS nominee Price close to home]]></title>
            <content>
                Representative Tom Price (R–GA), the physician and congressman who is Donald Trump’s nominee to head the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS), represents a wealthy suburban district just north of Atlanta that is regularly ranked by Forbes and others as one of the best places to live in the country.
                
                But Price’s district is also experiencing some public health crises that he will likely be dealing with as HHS Secretary: a serious heroin and opioid abuse epidemic, as well as elevated HIV infection rates.
                
                The heroin problem was described in great detail in this investigative special by the local NBC affiliate 11Alive, which aired in March 2016.  The narrator introduces the multipart series with the following stark facts:
                

            </content>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/drug-hiv-crises-hit-hhs-nominee-price-close-home</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 04:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/drug-hiv-crises-hit-hhs-nominee-price-close-home?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Congressman’s district among those facing serious public health woes]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Meredith Wadman]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Health, Policy, Science and Policy]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/cc_Price_16x9.jpg?itok=HbZ5ysrJ" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/cc_Price_16x9.jpg?itok=HbZ5ysrJ" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                Just north of Atlanta, heroin is killing more of our young people than violent crime. Atlanta’s most affluent area is dealing with a nearly 4000% increase in heroin-related deaths over the past 5 years.” She names as particular problems towns including Alpharetta, Roswell, and Johns Creek—all in the heart of Price’s district.
                
                Data released this week by the Big Cities Health Coalition Project further fleshes out the picture. It shows Fulton County—which takes up a chunk of Price’s district, as well as much of the city of Atlanta—with a higher rate of HIV diagnoses in 2013 and of accidental deaths from opioid overdoses in 2014 than all but one of 28 cities studied.
            </content>
            <title><![CDATA[You make more risky choices as the day wears on, chess study suggests]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/you-make-more-risky-choices-day-wears-chess-study-suggests</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 04:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/you-make-more-risky-choices-day-wears-chess-study-suggests?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Findings may apply to various aspects of life]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Devika G. Bansal]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Brain & Behavior]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/ep_iStock-462961143_16x9.jpg?itok=82HilpOn" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/ep_iStock-462961143_16x9.jpg?itok=82HilpOn" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                The problem has clearly caught the attention of some in the Price household. Price’s wife, Betty Price, an anesthesiologist who since 2015 has represented the couple’s home district in the Georgia House of Representatives, pushed through the Georgia House this last March a bill that would have liberalized state needle exchange programs. (Dirty needles used by injectable drug users are a prime source of HIV and hepatitis C infections.) Betty Price’s bill would have allowed counselors, programs for the homeless, drug treatment centers, and other organizations, in addition to doctors and pharmacists, to distribute sterile syringes to intravenous drug users. However, the bill failed in the state Senate, “due to some controversial aspects,” Betty Price told Georgia Health News.
                
                The other Dr. Price, on the other hand, voted to block U.S. funding for needle exchange programs in 2009, several years into his now-12-year stint representing Georgia’s 6th Congressional District in the U.S. House of Representatives. He also voted in 2007 to prevent the District of Columbia from using its own, nonfederal funds on needle exchange programs.
            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[Top stories: A real-time pollution model, a weird quantum distortion in space, and how to reactivate latent memories]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/top-stories-real-time-pollution-model-weird-quantum-distortion-space-and-how-reactivate</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 02:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/top-stories-real-time-pollution-model-weird-quantum-distortion-space-and-how-reactivate?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[The week’s top <i>Science</i> news]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Jessica Boddy]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Scientific Community]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/1202_roundup.jpg?itok=q8phHKhs" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/1202_roundup.jpg?itok=q8phHKhs" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                Europe’s ExoMars 2020 lander will go ahead as scheduled, despite the failure of the test-run Schiaparelli lander this past October, the European Space Agency (ESA) said today at the end of a council meeting at which government ministers from its 22 member states agreed on budgets for the next several years. ESA won a total of €10.3 billion for a wide range of projects extending into next decade but because the agency had requested €11 billion, some belt tightening will be required. And there was one notable casualty: the Asteroid Impact Mission (AIM), which planned to study in detail and land on a near-Earth asteroid in 2022, did not win enough support from member governments to proceed.
                

            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[Europe moves ahead with Mars mission, kills asteroid lander]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/europe-moves-ahead-mars-mission-kills-asteroid-lander</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 12:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/europe-moves-ahead-mars-mission-kills-asteroid-lander?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[European Space Agency also supports space station and looks far ahead to moon base]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Daniel Clery]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Europe, Space]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/1280x720_61028N_Exomars.jpg?itok=cmQo40kd" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/1280x720_61028N_Exomars.jpg?itok=cmQo40kd" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Institute of Medicine, and numerous other scientific bodies have found needle exchange programs to be highly effective in preventing the spread of HIV/AIDS and hepatitis C.
                
                It’s unclear whether, and to what extent, Tom Price’s experience of the opioid epidemic plaguing his home district will influence his priorities should the Senate confirm him as HHS Secretary; neither of the doctors Price was available for comment.
                
                At least one advocacy group, however, is not optimistic about the impact of a Tom Price tenure as secretary of the $1 trillion HHS. The Washington,D.C.,–based group Communities Advocating Emergency AIDS Relief issued a 30 November statement pronouncing itself “deeply concerned” by Price’s nomination, not least because of his intent to repeal Obamacare, which has allowed full health insurance coverage for many more people living with HIV.
            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[From shrinking spines to space fungus: The top five dangers of space travel]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/shrinking-spines-space-fungus-top-five-dangers-space-travel</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/shrinking-spines-space-fungus-top-five-dangers-space-travel?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[These hazards will make you think twice about relocating to Mars]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Jessica Boddy]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Brain & Behavior, Space]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/1_TopImage__16x9%281%29.jpg?itok=ppyEANHr" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/1_TopImage__16x9%281%29.jpg?itok=ppyEANHr" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                Testing for life would require anticipating a strong spectral signature of microbe byproducts like methane or oxygen, and then differentiating it from other processes, Faherty says. Another issue would be explaining how life could arise in an environment that lacks the water-rock interfaces, like hydrothermal vents, where life is thought to have begun on Earth. Perhaps life could develop through chemical reactions on the surfaces of dust grains in the brown dwarf’s atmosphere, or perhaps it gained a foothold after arriving as a hitchhiker on an asteroid. “Having little microbes that float in and out of a brown dwarf atmosphere is great,” Forgan says. “But you’ve got to get them there first.”
            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[Watch a dolphin swim with a first-of-its-kind artificial fluke ]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/watch-dolphin-swim-first-its-kind-artificial-fluke</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/watch-dolphin-swim-first-its-kind-artificial-fluke?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Study of dolphin amputee informs prosthetic design
            ]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Katherine Kornei]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Engineering, Plants & Animals]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/cc_winterDolphin_16x9.jpg?itok=csIqXMHF" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/cc_winterDolphin_16x9.jpg?itok=csIqXMHF" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                Early birds and night owls have radically different daily habits. But a new study suggests they both share one trait: As the clock ticks, their decisions get dicey. Neuroscientists examined the quality of moves in more than one million games of chess in an online database. They charted the decisions of 99 prolific players by gauging the time they took for each move and its usefulness in leading to a victory—factors that impact games like high-speed tiebreakers in the World Chess Championships, which took place in New York earlier this week. As expected, early risers played more games in the morning, whereas night owls were active at dusk and beyond. But both sets of players took longer for each move and made better game choices early in the day and soon after they woke up. Come evening, their game play quickened by ...
            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[Alien life could thrive in the clouds of failed stars ]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/alien-life-could-thrive-clouds-failed-stars</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 03:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/alien-life-could-thrive-clouds-failed-stars?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Mild temperatures one benefit to worlds more massive than Jupiter]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Joshua Sokol]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Space]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/ep_SciSource_SB2454_16x9.jpg?itok=skK29pUM" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/ep_SciSource_SB2454_16x9.jpg?itok=skK29pUM" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                The idea is speculative but worth considering, says Duncan Forgan, an astrobiologist at the University of St. Andrews in the United Kingdom, who did not participate in the study but says he is close to the team. “It really opens up the field in terms of the number of objects that we might then think, well, these are habitable regions.”
                
                So far, only a few dozen cold brown dwarfs have been discovered, though statistics suggest there should be about 10 within 30 light-years of Earth. These should be ripe targets for the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), which is sensitive in the infrared where brown dwarfs shine brightest. After it launches in 2018, the JWST should reveal the weather and the composition of their atmospheres, says Jackie Faherty, an astronomer at the Carnegie Institution for Science in Washington, D.C. “We’re going to start getting gorgeous spectra of these objects,” she says. “This is making me think about it.”
            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[Misconduct allegations fly in spat over paper on microplastics and fish larvae]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/misconduct-allegations-fly-spat-over-paper-microplastics-and-fish-larvae</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 05:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/misconduct-allegations-fly-spat-over-paper-microplastics-and-fish-larvae?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Science publishes “expression of editorial concern” because raw data are missing]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Martin Enserink]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Scientific Community]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/ep_iStock-520975140_16x9.jpg?itok=XmNfRwnJ" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/ep_iStock-520975140_16x9.jpg?itok=XmNfRwnJ" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                There’s an abundant new swath of cosmic real estate that life could call home—and the views would be spectacular. Floating out by themselves in the Milky Way galaxy are perhaps a billion cold brown dwarfs, objects many times as massive as Jupiter but not big enough to ignite as a star. According to a new study, layers of their upper atmospheres sit at temperatures and pressures resembling those on Earth, and could host microbes that surf on thermal updrafts.
                
                The idea expands the concept of a habitable zone to include a vast population of worlds that had previously gone unconsidered. “You don’t necessarily need to have a terrestrial planet with a surface,” says Jack Yates, a planetary scientist at the University of Edinburgh in the United Kingdom, who led the study.
            </content>

            <title><![CDATA[Maryland congressman in running to head NIH?]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/maryland-congressman-running-head-nih</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 05:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/maryland-congressman-running-head-nih?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Representative Andy Harris (R–MD) doesn’t fit the usual mold to head the biomedical research agency]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Jocelyn Kaiser]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/Andy%20Harris.jpg?itok=fB84zRng" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/Andy%20Harris.jpg?itok=fB84zRng" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <content>
                Yates and his colleagues applied the same thinking to a kind of world Sagan didn’t know about. Discovered in 2011, some cold brown dwarfs have surfaces roughly at room temperature or below; lower layers would be downright comfortable. In March 2013, astronomers discovered WISE 0855-0714, a brown dwarf only 7 light-years away that seems to have water clouds in its atmosphere. Yates and his colleagues set out to update Sagan’s calculations and to identify the sizes, densities, and life strategies of microbes that could manage to stay aloft in the habitable region of an enormous atmosphere of predominantly hydrogen gas. Sink too low and you are cooked or crushed. Rise too high and you might freeze.
                
                On such a world, small sinkers like the microbes in Earth’s atmosphere or even smaller would have a better chance than Sagan’s floaters, the researchers will report in an upcoming issue of The Astrophysical Journal. But a lot depends on the weather: If upwelling winds are powerful on free-floating brown dwarfs, as seems to be true in the bands of gas giants like Jupiter and Saturn, heavier creatures can carve out a niche. In the absence of sunlight, they could feed on chemical nutrients. Observations of cold brown dwarf atmospheres reveal most of the ingredients Earth life depends on: carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen, and oxygen, though perhaps not phosphorous.
            </content>
            <title><![CDATA[Extreme tornado outbreaks are getting worse, but why?]]></title>
            <link>http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/extreme-tornado-outbreaks-are-getting-worse-why</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 02:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/12/extreme-tornado-outbreaks-are-getting-worse-why?rss=1</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Rise may not be related to climate change]]></description>
            <media:credit role="author"><![CDATA[Sid Perkins]]></media:credit>
            <media:category><![CDATA[Climate, Earth]]></media:category>
            <media:content url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/cc_AP12954066566_v2_16x9.jpg?itok=KET_7mkW" height="266" width="127" />
            <media:thumbnail url="http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_teaser/public/images/cc_AP12954066566_v2_16x9.jpg?itok=KET_7mkW" height="266" width="127" />
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
